Great. As I mentioned at the beginning, the second
part of today is going to be on negotiation
skills. Assuming you can present well, eventually
you'll then have to engage with the people
that want to know more, and there are skills
that can be learned about that. We have Mindy
Garber, who's done this a number of times.
I'm going to let Mindy, like others that have
presented, introduce themselves. I hope you enjoy this,
and I know you'll get a lot out
of it. Mindy?
Good evening, and welcome, and thank you
for coming. Most ventures fail because of people
issues and are really a failure of the
relationships among the team members. That quote was an
inspiration for this workshop. Here's the original
paper that it came from a while ago,
but it's just as valuable.
Mindy Garber, I'm a class of 82, and I'm
both an engineer and a mediator. I tell people
the difference between engineering and mediation is,
as an engineer, your job is to gather
all the facts.
Mindy Garber, I'm a class of 82, and I'm
both an engineer and a mediator. I tell people,
the difference between engineering and mediation is,
as an engineer, your job is to gather
all the facts. You're trying to do
that. You're trying to form a relationship and
make the optimal solution. As a mediator,
you're trying to help people have a conversation
that they couldn't have before, and you're
trying to help them communicate with each
other, and help them figure out why they,
you know, to help them solve their own problems.
So, that's how I got into it. I
got into mediation because, really, after financial issues, when
I helped start a company that
does speech recognition, after financial issues, getting
along is really the hardest part.
Mindy Garber, I'm a class of 82, and I'm
both an engineer and a mediator. I tell people,
that's really the hardest part.
And I've seen a lot of companies
fail, not because of technology problems or financial,
but because the two founders couldn't get along.
And that leads to a lot of wasted IP.
And so anything that we can do to
help companies be successful and monetize their IP,
it's something that will be a
good thing for the U.S. economy.
Okay, so this course is very interactive.
And the people on Zoom, you
don't get a buy on this.
There's stuff for you to do, too.
But I want to please raise your hand.
And for now, could everybody get a partner?
And if it's the person that
you are a co-founder with, that's fine.
But for now, you're just going to be co-founders.
So please pick somebody else, because
otherwise this class will be no fun.
All right.
Okay.
That's one way to get people to move.
It's so funny, because when I was a student, I always
would sit in the back, too, and now I get it.
It's like, please, please, if you want, come forward.
Okay.
All right.
So the agenda.
We're going to talk a little bit about negotiation.
We're going to talk about startup negotiations.
And when you're starting up, it's you're
negotiating with your co-founder, with the intercompany,
and intercompany, between other companies.
And then we have a bunch of role
plays along the way, and we'll do a debrief.
Okay.
So there are many schools of thought of negotiation.
But basically, there's two kinds of ideas.
There's an idea that it's either
win-lose, or it's more of a collaboration.
If it's a win-lose, you're trying to get as
most, you know, you think it's a zero-sum game.
I win.
You lose.
If I get something, you lose something.
And also, you don't really necessarily
care about the relationship between the people.
But if it's a collaboration, and it's
two people working on the problem together.
So my whole philosophy is
all based on getting to yes.
And I took the negotiation, the program
on negotiation at Harvard, which I highly recommend.
So it's a joint effort.
You're collaborating.
It's a problem.
And you do care about the relationship.
And this is, and I know
that Joe has a million stories, too.
There is no such thing as one and done.
People think, oh, I'm just going to do this,
and I'm never going to see this guy again.
Well, we both have a lot of stories, if there's time at the end,
to tell you how what you negotiate today may come back to haunt you.
Even if it's the person goes to another
company and decides never to buy your product again.
You will always meet people again.
And so being a...
A principled negotiator is a very important thing.
Your reputation will precede you.
So the first thing to think about in
a negotiation is for you, what are your interests?
What are your needs and goals and hopes and fears?
What is it you want?
There's a lot of people when I'm in mediation and
you ask people, OK, well, what is it you want?
People have no idea.
They haven't really thought about it.
It's like, well, how can I?
How can you solve it?
How can you solve your problem if it isn't?
You don't really even know why it is you're doing things and
having your own interests and understanding them really leads to having options.
If you know what you want, you can say, well,
there may be a lot of different solutions to getting it.
So I just put this picture in the this is
a sort of stereotypical negotiation is like people have positions.
You know, I want five hundred dollars.
And then if you ask them why?
Why do you need five hundred dollars?
They'll say, well, you know, you drove over my fence
and it's going to cost five hundred dollars to fix it.
So that's the that's the interest is
that I need to fix my fence.
I could say, well, my brother fixes fences and he'll do it and
he'll make it as good as new and you won't have to pay anything.
So now I've had an option of the options are all the things that
solve the that solve your interests that that you may not have thought of.
So typically as an engineer.
We come in and say, here is the right answer.
You know, we need to program this in C++.
And then you'd say, well, like, why is it?
Well, if I have to learn some other language,
it'll take me six months to learn that language.
But I already know C++, so
I can do it in three weeks.
So you have to get to even I teach a moderating
design dispute in one of the design courses to double nine.
And it's really just helping people
understand why people want what they want.
OK.
So now we're getting to the negotiations.
So the first things you're going
to do is talk amongst yourselves.
Then you're going to have negotiations
within your company as it grows.
And you're going to have to talk to people outside your company, not just just
not just your customers, but your vendors, your people that you work with and collaborate with.
So you're going to have all kinds of negotiations.
So we talk about we talk.
About the kinds of negotiations the founders should have.
And I've divided into three parts.
One is first questions.
And we'll get to these in details.
Everybody's heard of a founders agreement.
And we'll talk a little bit about that.
And then there's the team agreement.
So first questions are really why
are why are you doing this.
What does success look like.
And what are you giving up to do this venture.
And I think the third question is really
the most one of the most important because people.
Say oh I'm giving up grad school or I got this great
job with Google but I'm giving it up to to work on this.
And it's really important to know where people come from.
So what I'd like you to do
is for about two minutes with your co-founder.
Don't give information that's secret to your company but you
could but ask each other these questions and answer them.
Now what I want to also stress here is the
person when you ask your co-founder why are you doing this.
They're going to give you some
answer instead of just moving on.
We're going to practice active listening and just reframe it say so you are doing
this to you know to further the further the science in your field whatever it is.
And this way every both sides feel heard.
And we're going to ask and answer these questions.
OK.
Give like two minutes or three minutes.
How are we doing up there.
Let's stop for a minute.
How many of you are planning
to found a company with another person.
Please raise your hand.
Keep your hands raised.
If you have already had this discussion.
OK.
One person.
So what you're doing here is
you're finding out each other's interests.
I have my slides in the wrong order so I'm
going to skip a slide but I will come back.
To it.
So what I tell people to do is this is called the circle of interests where you write a
circle and then you put each person's you know a little stick for each person and write their interests down.
And the reason you do this is so that
you literally get all of your interests on one page.
So this is what I did.
I mentored a startup and we sat and I actually asked them the questions
and I took down their answers and you can see one of them is.
I'm trying to solve a problem
that's been identified but not yet solved.
I want to learn about tech.
I don't know about tech
but I wanted to challenge myself.
I want to challenge myself
to learn something I know nothing.
I'm good at detail and I
want to keep expanding my skills.
And the other founder said well
I want to be a successful entrepreneur.
I want to show how a successful venture can change the format
or help a certain section of people and be a profitable company.
So they gave me all these things I wrote them
down and then I looked at them and I said.
Oh so have you heard any you.
You haven't heard anything that
you haven't heard before right here.
And they kind of gave me a very sheepish look
and they hadn't discussed it because they had a great idea.
They both wanted to do it but they didn't
know why the other person wanted to do it.
Right.
So I feel like this is.
Well let me ask you this.
Do you think this is important when starting a company.
OK.
So let me go back to this slide that I skipped because
I went back and forth what order these things should be in.
And.
This this slide I added because pretty much after every one of
these lectures people will how do I know who's a good co-founder.
How do I know how should I pick them.
And the thing is this is where I
call the discussion that you have your honest assessment.
What skills do we each bring and what are our personalities to really discuss like
oh I really love being in front of people and I will talk people's ears off.
Whereas some people are like well maybe that kind of function
you should take over because I'm not so interested in doing that.
But what I am not saying is let's just say you're
two mechanical engineers and you have an idea for a widget.
I am not saying you should not form a
company together because you have the exact same skills.
What I am saying is that when you form your company with you know you know your
skill set and you're going to say oh we will need additional skills to help this company.
Right.
So it's not saying who you should and shouldn't
you know be with as far as your technical skills.
It's just understanding that.
There's a lot of skills needed to start a company and knowing
which ones you have and which ones you don't have are really important.
OK.
All right.
So the next one is the founders agreement and I'm not going to spend
too much time on it because there are lots and lots of books written.
In fact even MIT has has a
book on how to write a founders agreement.
But basically it's just covering who owns what.
You know who did what who's contributing what.
And your very favorite the equity discussion.
How many people are looking forward to
having an equity discussion with their co-founder.
OK.
So you already had it.
You guys already had your equity discussions.
No the people.
Oh no.
You're just you're just OK.
Fine.
All right.
And the most important thing is what happens if one founder leaves and
that's a really like OK I decided I am going to grad school.
And see you later.
And having these discussions and writing everything down.
And the thing with equity is like suppose I'm the inventor and the other person
is sort of the business person and we're like oh we could form a company.
Well at the beginning of the company I'm doing all the work and maybe as
the company goes on I do less and less and people take more and more.
So it's really about what your contributions are what are the values of the
contribution you make to the company and being able to just have a real discussion.
What does it take to put this company together.
And who's going to do what.
And what are the pieces and
what are the values of the pieces.
So this is just something that
you're going to have to talk about.
And again there's lots of
lots of literature to help you.
So the last thing is about the team agreement.
So what is a team agreement.
So anytime two or more
people work together it's a team.
Right.
So like I do a lot of co-mediation.
That's a team.
And the agreement is how
are we going to work together.
And I think all companies have it
but it's sort of like the secret thing.
You know when you go work for
a company it's like oh who knows this.
How do you get that done.
How do we communicate.
Which slack channels are we supposed to be using.
All the things that that you
have to learn as a new employee.
You could actually write down in advance and and
and create the culture for your company that you want.
And MIT really does push having team agreements.
And I'm a mentor for the
UPAP program which is undergraduate practice opportunities.
And on the first day they have to write an
agreement on how they're going to interact with each other.
So the kind of corporate culture you want what
are the rules and how decisions will be made.
So the first thing is is the culture.
Now there's company ethics and of course we
can argue Google did have its original ethics.
Don't be evil.
You might argue well maybe now it's.
Be less evil.
It's not.
More evil than everyone else.
But they they did have one originally.
And what do you expect for people to do.
How are you expecting people to behave to each other.
And again as you start your company if you don't think about
these things your first employees are going to create the culture for you.
So this is your chance to do two things set up the kind of culture you want to work
in and you want others to work in and also have a way to communicate it with each other.
So this is like how are you going to interact.
How are we going to have meetings.
So I just co-founded a venture which is a nonprofit that
we're really just teaching workshops and I set these things up.
We're going to we're going to have a Monday morning meeting
you know and we're going to talk about the following things.
And how are we going to plan and
how are we going to share and collaborate.
And just even saying OK we'll use Google Docs
or we'll use Slack or whatever it is is important.
The other thing is next we have roles.
Who's going to do what.
And how are we going
to be accountable to each other.
So how are we going to manage it.
How are we going to
understand like what's going to happen.
And again this does two things not just sets the
stage but it also gives you a way to communicate.
Hey you know in our team agreement we said that we would you
know have our meetings Monday at three o'clock every you know every Monday.
And maybe that's not working now or you seem
to be not available every Monday at three o'clock.
So it's giving you the
language to talk to each other.
Instead of sort of accusing each other whatever.
These are things you've agreed to.
You can change them.
And that's the other thing is
all these things should be revisited.
Everything that you do.
I have a co-founders check in
you know every six months or so.
How are we doing.
And it's really not about what we're doing it's
about how are we working together as a team.
OK.
So the last thing is
how will the team make decisions.
And what will you do if you disagree.
So.
So I'm going to give you like two
minutes to talk to your co-founder and you each.
First of all the people that are co-founding how many people
have 50 50 agreements like we each own half the company.
OK.
So assume that you co-founder you're all
50 50 have a discussion with you.
What can you do when you disagree on something.
OK.
I'll give you like two minutes.
Hey.
OK.
Raise your hand and I'll call on you.
Who has some suggestions as to what to do.
What to do with if you can't agree.
Raise your raise your hand.
I'm giving each other some time
to discuss over what was being discussed.
I have bullet points.
But.
I'm probably.
Afterwards.
Lock each other together in the room.
Or go for if preferred for coffee or something.
OK.
Then discuss honestly about everything should be honest of what their opinion
was and how they think they could come together to a probable solution.
But.
The conversation.
Should be honest.
Once we exit the room there should
be nothing that's held back so that.
For the collective vision we can move forward
from that problem because there's many others to come.
OK.
So step back think about it
and have a real intense discussion.
Who else has some other ideas.
So.
It also depends on.
At which point of disagreement you are.
It is a point of blockage of the business
potentially one that will impact the growth of the business.
It has to be a point
that will have a form of resolution.
So in the past that level of disagreement I put
in the agreement from the beginning basically a Wesleyan approach.
We will agree to disagree and
this is what we will do.
Prior to that you should try
to not be at that level.
And then.
Try to get some form of mediation.
So finding a neutral ground going to move either sharing a
meal is one thing that it gets the businesses more mature.
Finding ways to not get to that level of disagreement and how if
there's not an imbalance of power how you can get a joint decision.
OK.
Good.
Over here.
So one thing that we
were talking about is if you.
We.
Are.
Agree on something that we should find like an advice person that would like consultants that
will help us and we should agree that we will go without being on that advice person.
That is the next person.
OK.
Consultant.
Great.
Are there any other ideas.
Oh they're back there.
So.
We also talked about the type of decision that remains.
So if it's a one way type of decision so
it's very hard to come back or take it back.
Then we discuss a lot on it.
We go very truthfully.
Truthfully.
Right.
We put a lot of investment and
we come up with a decision together.
Right.
Either.
We can also work outside.
Or.
Guidance or something like that.
But if it's a two way
decision so we can make it.
And then it's not that hard
to come back with that decision.
We can just evaluate.
Just like make the decision.
Example.
What is the.
What is the benefit from that decision.
OK.
So the severity decision make it
and see see how it goes.
Good.
Summarize that a little bit.
Just like.
Yeah.
You know.
Like a one way decision.
Where it's like you know once you go back.
Or once you go to it.
Can't really come back with it.
Just take it a little bit of
the way and then see how it goes.
And then like go from there.
OK.
If it doesn't work out.
Go with the other person.
OK.
So decide and then maybe you
can back out if it's not good.
So there's the get advice from an
expert or MIT venture mentoring kind of people.
Consultants.
You know some companies take turns being the decider.
But.
So I have another.
Workshop that I used to teach called helping small businesses avoid
court based on all of the mediations that I had done.
And so I have.
I also do arbitration which is where I'm the decider.
So I talked to one of my
lawyer friends and I said oh can you.
You know you've done a lot
of litigation on with small companies.
Can you tell me what you
know I'm working on this workshop.
Can you help me.
And he looks at me says never
ever let anyone be 50 be 50 50.
Make it 51.
And then he starts telling me all the court
cases that he had where he sued the other partner.
And at one point there was like a.
The two partners got in a fight in the courtroom.
And so.
So he's like telling me doing that and I said I
laughed at him I said you know it's funny you say that.
But 100 percent of the people
that I've ever met are 50 50.
So we better give them the
tools so that they can avoid you.
So they don't have what they
don't wind up being at lawyers.
So that's sort of where this is that this.
Has started out from.
OK good.
So now we're going to get to the
role play and I need a couple of volunteers.
So.
You have in your pairs one of
you is going to be the inventor Sandra.
And one of you is going to be a student.
And Sandra and this is a true story.
This happened here at MIT.
And Joe knows the people involved
and I know the people involved.
Sandra has invented a very
inexpensive way to process crude oil.
So.
I need I have three slides I used to
hand out pieces of paper for people to read.
But I need volunteers to read the slides.
So do I have a
volunteer who will read one slide.
Thank you.
Then I need to read the second one.
OK here we go.
Read this slide please.
I know.
It's cheaper than handing out paper that no one wants.
Yeah.
Yes verbatim just read it.
Very.
Overview.
Sandra has a.
Name but you've done that it can only
process one cup of crude oil at a time.
Several undergraduates try to run this.
And then you still take it up and
somehow it was decided to end with a
hundred.
Division.
And perhaps start a company.
Ten to City.
Between the inventor and her.
I stone mox with.
The under contents.
Starting seating.
On.
The.
Attempts.
To.
devastated more.
Of.
He.
Can.
On.
You.
who of course were very invested in the invention.
They put in a tremendous
amount of work in this venture,
sometimes to the determent of their regular task work.
Just before the competition, however,
Sandra is taking off pulling it out.
Saying that her invention isn't great.
This would leave the students disappointed and frustrated
that all their work has been for nothing.
OK, next one.
That's so smart.
Sandra's invention could only process
one cup of food at a time.
And she isn't sure how to scale it up,
or even if the process is scalable.
She has no written agreement with the students.
And she isn't even sure the students are
capable of starting a company.
In the end, though, it is her invention.
And she feels that she can
decide what to do with it.
I need one more reader.
Anyone else want to read one?
OK.
They are in the AU Center.
She had a PhD and has invented something
that could be really useful and profitable.
They are hesitant to bring up uncomfortable subjects
like agreements, with her assuming that it will all
work out after they have proven
to her how much effort they're
willing to put in to make the company a success.
They can't understand her reluctance
to move forward faster.
When they get a company executive interested,
she doesn't seem that excited to speak with them.
Also, she doesn't seem to really want
to show her invention to
anyone, even though from the outside,
it just looks like a black box.
And no one would be
able to see the inside process.
OK.
So one of you is Sandra.
And one of you is the students.
But first of all, I'd like you to discuss
what are your interests.
So take a couple minutes.
OK.
So take a couple minutes and tell each other
what your interests are.
And actually, you can think about the other person's too.
So if you're a student,
you can think, oh, maybe Sandra
might be interested in this.
So think about the interests
of both Sandra and the student.
And I'll give you a few minutes.
People at home, write down all the interests
that you can think of
for both Sandra and the students.
Who would you like to talk with?
Hey, we're going to fill our little interest thing.
I can't do it what you're saying.
But let's start with the student's interest.
And she's just going to hand it.
People in the corner, just
say something, a student interest,
and then hand it to the person next to you.
A student interest is fun and exciting
and could be a cool experience for them.
A student.
OK.
So they want a fun experience.
next a student okay we could say
Sandra whatever okay wanting to protect her IP
so why do they want to raise
money what what what are their interests
profitable venture okay so she's worried about
her reputation do you want to hand
it down to the next row
yeah I would repeat what they phrase it
okay would say that the students are more
concerned of the process and some drum
more concern about the result so the
students want to get experience in
starting a company and Sanders really
worried about her reputation and
being able to to build the
wiedersehen they don't want toSlap hands up anything D
he's no pain and really Assistant Smoothie
in avereko
hi
more concerns
yeah
purpose like oh no I can't do my
homework I have to work on this project
I mean is it like what's an interest
maybe it's also like a good cost kind of thing where they spend
time on this and they could have been doing time on the work instead
okay so they want to return
on their investment yeah of time okay
right are there other ideas okay
actually go here first and then then
back oh okay that's okay go ahead that's
fine okay so she is in control yeah okay
anyone else on this line okay
yeah
so Suncraft is focused on the Wagner Technology
trying to make it scalable and
gradually be able to use it ...
the students you know here I was students and they...
they need one internship they need one job
and to put this into a 24 hour program
know into their own resume, you know, graduate. So
their work and some of us seem a little different.
And maybe I have one there.
No, this is good. So possibly they just want to put it on their
resume, but maybe they don't, they want this to be their career, their job.
Maybe they just, you know, this is like, oh, look, if I do this and it's
successful, I have a job coming out of school and I can do something that's worthwhile.
So are there any other
things that you felt weren't covered?
OK, so over the over the years, we've collected a bunch
of things and actually from the from the real people, too.
But here. So the students get it. And
again, they're this is not the right answer.
You guys had answers. I mean, this is when you're
thinking about people's interests, you don't necessarily always get them right.
And I'll go to, you know, even
when I'm in a mediation, I'll say,
OK, I'm going to do
this. I'm going to do this.
So you're interested in this. And they'll go,
no, I'm not interested in that at all.
But I am interested in why. Right.
So, again, this is not the right answer.
These are just things that have
since I couldn't really do it live.
Things that people have thought up over the years.
You know, there's a career path with the company.
The students, they are learning to talk with executives.
I mean, they're talking to
senior executives at oil companies. Right.
They are bringing a new
technology that will help the world.
So they're like, wow, this will be great.
If we could really cut down on what it takes to process crude oil,
maybe we would, you know, save a lot of energy, obviously money and career.
And for her, she wants to protect her IP,
which you said about that, that she wants control.
But she also is very concerned about her
own, you know, her own reputation in the field.
She doesn't want to say, oh, I have this, you know, because scaling up
from one cup to, you know, a million gallons a day is not, you know,
an easy thing to do.
So what you're going to do now, student and Sandra, are you're going to pick the things
that you thought of that were interests and come up with an agreement that would meet your interests.
OK, so you're going to get a
little bit longer to talk about this.
You can pick a couple of things, two
or three things and come up with them.
If you were going to go
forward with this, what would you do?
If you were going to go forward with
this, what kind of agreement would meet your interests?
So pick a couple of your interests, the ones that you thought of, or if
you want to pick from there and let's see what agreements you can come up with.
OK.
OK, so how many of you raise your hand if
you were able to come to some kind of agreement?
OK.
So for the people who.
Who came to an agreement, can you
tell us something that you agreed to?
And I wanted to make one other comment
before that someone came up and mentioned to me.
So sometimes it's hard to understand what
our interests and what our positions like.
I want to I want to raise capital.
Well, then it's what are the interests behind the capital?
What is it?
What is it going to do for you?
Why do you want to raise the capital?
So these are interests, what they what they want, what they're what
they're interested, what their fears are, as opposed to, you know, you know,
they think they're going to win.
They could say, I want to make a million dollars.
Well, that's an interest.
Right.
So it's but we'll keep going through this and
coming down to what are interests versus versus positions.
OK.
So who wants to share something that they
agreed to that they could both agree to?
We could go first.
So we came to the agreement
that it could be a joint venture.
But Sandra has all the
idea of the package and everything.
And she comes to like.
I thought it was a beautiful license.
We are part of this business.
Specifically, there's like a discounted significantly discounted rate for the
students to manufacture and use it for the first 10 years.
And then it's only with time that change.
Also, like her position in the company might not
be as a co-founder, but more as an advisor.
OK.
She doesn't need to be in the limelight.
But at the same time, she has ownership.
She has shares.
She could have an agreement with the revenue
share law to come to her because her license
already has money and we put
an additional revenue stream for her.
The way I see it is that
students have the most incentive to do it.
But because Sandra has the idea, the
students have to take the most risk.
Sandra is like the queen bee in this situation.
She has the main thing that's doing
this whole thing together, taking this on.
And yeah.
Yeah.
OK.
So good.
And that's an agreement you
both would agree to and sign.
Who else had something?
Who else agreed to something?
Did you guys have an agreement?
So in our case, she made the point that Sandra does
deserve a lot of equity because of her experience in the IT.
But I need to point that although IT is
a very good thing, it's not a good thing.
It's not a good thing.
And we're not trying to do this because we
want to do it because it's a good thing.
So we are trying to do this because we want
to do it because we want to do it because it's
good for the company.
And also, although IP, there
is no business without the IP.
There is also no business without marketing,
but functions that are required in the company.
So we decided to come up with
a number for each of these functions.
So first take it up,
you know, a bunch of functions.
Come up with a number for each of these functions.
And have an honest discussion
about who would perform which function.
And according to that, we divide.
OK.
So base equity on all the different requirements
and who's gonna do what and then talk about that.
Okay, so you did agree
to have a joint venture together.
Okay, who else?
So I mean, overall we had a lot more disagreements
but one thing we did talk about was like
maybe using patents to protect
her IP for a little bit
so that she could have some control over it
while giving like company control over to someone else.
Okay, so what were your challenges?
Yeah, I mean the challenge is like,
it sounds kind of like
Sandra wants to have her KTE
to do a little bit because like, you know,
she wants to protect her IP
and like have control over it,
right, but at the same time she doesn't want
to run her own business
and like she wants to stay
under the limelight and that kind of like, you know,
interferes with like wanting to grow and everything, so.
So she's ambivalent about doing this in general.
That's what it sounds like.
Okay, so who else had some challenges
that would like to share?
Okay.
It might be different but just thinking about it.
Since students cannot really take that much risk,
why not use this as a research project
where, you know, you can improve
on a product, how to scale,
scale them, you can get grants to, you know,
still make money if you can make money,
but both parties can still be protected
because it's a research.
You don't have to like make any promises.
Okay, so instead of starting a company,
let's research to how we can scale it up.
Is that what you're saying?
So let's put in money, we're gonna research,
we're gonna get grants to see if it is scalable
and that way if I'm Sandra, I feel more comfortable
and that you feel more comfortable
that this is gonna be a real product
and a viable product.
Okay, that's a really great idea.
Are there any other challenges that you couldn't come
to an agreement because of challenges?
Okay, so what really happened?
How many of you think they had any agreement?
Raise your hand.
Okay, so they didn't.
But let me ask you this
before we go to the answer.
Is this a one of, does this ever happen?
Is this just like one time at MIT this happened
and it doesn't happen ever?
What are your thoughts?
Do you think this is,
do you ever hear of things like this happening?
Joe, do you wanna say something?
Okay, so they didn't have any agreement
and they were never able to
really talk about what they wanted
and what they thought Sandra wanted.
And she took her invention and started a different company
with a whole different set of people.
So it was a great, excellent learning experience
for the students.
I wanna just tell you, PS, they all graduated
and they all have lovely careers.
But they were not able
to have this discussion with them.
And at the time I
sort of begged them, I said,
let me help you, I'll just be the neutral person.
I'll help you have a discussion with her.
And they're like, no, no, it'll work out.
We're working really hard.
It'll work out.
So that's what happened.
And she still has her company
and I don't really know how successful it was,
but it's still an ongoing company.
So that was that.
Was this useful to go through this exercise?
Was this helpful to you to think about things
from both sides.
Okay, because this is a good question.
because we're gonna just go do a couple
more of these okay so actually so this
is your agreements so now you're now
you have a company and you negotiate gonna
gonna gonna negotiate within a company
within people and again there might be
differences in power levels you might
have legal ramifications there may be
more than two parties and it
may require another level of confidentiality but
again even when I'm having difficulties
with someone I always draw my little
circle of interests and really try to
understand what is it that people are
interested in and can I position my
interest in the terms of other interests
so I sort of given you this is an
example and this is this is based on two
people that I that I mentored so Judy
wants to get a promotion in as a
marketing manager by the way is there a talent
acquisition
module in this in is there a
talent acquisition module in your course no
okay so in the field of
talent acquisition this is thinking about how
people get hired and who you hire but
this is example Judy wanted to apply to
be a marketing manager and so I had
to go through each sort of interested party
and these are all the stakeholders
what could they possibly be thinking about
what would be interest them so the
manager wants to look like hey I'm this
great manager I'm growing my employees right
so they will they can take on more
responsibility and and also but I need
to get all my work done so Judy's
interest well I want to contribute more to
this company you know I want to be
seen as very competent I want to start
supervising others I want to I want to
be part of a really high achieving team
I want more challenging work I want I
want to use my newly gained skills
so what does the company want well
of course what company doesn't want revenue
but they also want effective leadership
and they want to grow their employees
they want to have more diversity they
want more you know more client projects
but then she has teammates they probably
want a promotion too but just thinking
about so thinking about all of these things
and so what it did is it actually
helped her go to her manager but before
she did that I said okay well you want
to be a marketing manager here's all
the things that a marketing manager could do
this is not the exhaustive list but I'm
just saying and then you don't have to
it's just everything that anyone could
think about in marketing and actually
the company that I that I was a
founder of these were these were all the things
that we had to do for marketing I'm
not in market I was the engineering but the
marketing people did and so I sent her
this list and I just didn't do anything
I just said okay well okay I think we're doing a great job now I think
that's a great way to wrap things up for us so we can do something else.
here's some of the things that marketing is responsible for.
So what she did on her
own is she made an Excel spreadsheet
and put every one of
those things in the Excel spreadsheet.
She gave them a value of one, two, three,
how important it was.
And she came up with, on her own,
she came up with a strategy
of what she was gonna do
and how she was going to
go through all of these things,
even though this is not necessarily
the be all and end all list.
And so when she went to talk about her promotion,
she talked about interests and then she also presented,
well, here's what I, she actually presented her report
and here's all the things we need to do
and here's how I think we could start them.
And so she sort of had presented it
like she'd already done the job.
So she did get the job.
So anyway, but it all started with thinking about
what are other people's interests
and then thinking about how can you meet those interests?
How can you prove that you're competent?
How can you prove that
you're ready for this new step?
So that's that one.
Okay, so this is the last one,
is you're gonna have to negotiate with other companies.
And this is a true story.
So this is what happened to me.
I'm Little Inc.
And we had a contract with Big Inc.
And it was a fixed cost contract,
meaning they just paid us upfront for everything.
But in the contract, it said,
we can cancel for any
time, any time that we want.
And if we do, well, we
realize you may have done some work.
So we'll pay you for time and materials
of what you've already done.
And you'll come, well, and literally the contract
was so vague, it said something like,
we'll figure out how much you owe.
Someone will figure out somewhere how much you owe.
And so this is the thing about contracts.
You can have a 300 page contract.
It isn't gonna cover everything.
You can think of it's not gonna.
So it was very vague.
And they basically, they didn't cancel the contract
because of our work.
The company, the Big Inc was actually having
more financial issues and they needed,
they canceled all of their contracts.
So we were just one of them,
but probably on the smaller side.
So they said, we're gonna need some money back.
And we'll talk about, we'll tell you
what we're gonna do later.
So I met with,
I was as manager, or not manager,
but just as representing service.
We had a CFO, the chief financial officer,
and the salesperson who actually sold it.
So we went around the room and everybody said,
we said, I think we should do this.
I think we should do that.
And that got us nowhere.
So I said, how about this?
Why don't we sit down and
think about all of our interests
and we'll think of the interests of the other company,
and then see if we can
come up with a solution space
that would work for us
before we even meet with them.
So, let's see.
So now we have Little Inc has sales executive.
We have the service manager, me,
and we have the CFO,
and then we have Big Inc.
So for this contract,
well let's start with the easiest one.
What might,
what might the sales executive's concern be?
Like, oh my God, the contract was canceled,
we're gonna have to give back money.
What was his concern?
What's coming to my commission?
That's right, what happens to my commission?
So that's what he was mostly worried about.
And so let's talk about the service manager, me.
What was I concerned about?
Your reputation.
My reputation.
What else?
Your job.
My job.
My job?
We lost a contract?
What else?
What does customer support care about?
Customers.
Customers, and what?
The relationship, right?
So what did I care about?
They had been a customer for a really long time,
and we had other stuff going on with them,
so this was not a one-time deal.
We had other contracts with them.
So other interests.
And let me just tell you,
we came up with three pages.
Three pages of interest.
Okay, let's talk about our CFO.
What was her interest?
What's the problem with giving money back?
Accounting, so they need to
have cash to give them back.
Cash flow.
Worried about the company.
What else?
Depends on what happens.
If it's after the closing of the books,
it's really problematic.
Okay, so in other words,
if we've already declared the revenue
because we got the cash,
did we already declare it all,
or do we declare it
like month by month or whatever?
How we declared it, and can
we go back and undeclare it?
So that was that.
But there were a lot of personal things, too.
For example, one of her
concerns was, I don't want them
to think this is David and Goliath.
I don't want them to
think this is David and Goliath.
And they're just stomping all over us.
I wanted them to feel
like we are a real company.
We were a 20-person company,
and they were like 10,000 people.
But the two of us
were agreed on a couple things.
One, we did not want
this to escalate to the CEO,
even though that was just one level up.
In a 20-person company, there's only one or two levels.
We did not want it to go to the CEO.
We did not want lawyers involved, because that
wouldn't have done any good.
And so we really wanted
to keep it at our level.
But now think about our contact at Big Inc.
What was Big Inc. worried about?
Probably their reputation.
Their reputation.
So they were like, oh,
we bought something from Little Inc.
and we canceled it.
And who cares?
We stomp all over little companies.
What else?
Legal.
Maybe they'll sue us, because we've already paid them,
and they've done so much of the work.
Maybe they don't know what we're thinking.
And we didn't know what they were thinking either.
So what else?
Someone messed up, and they
would want to protect themselves.
Right.
So how about the person who bought this and signed
the contract?
Like, oh my god, I signed the contract.
And now they canceled it.
Like, what's my reputation going to be like?
OK.
So here's the interest that we came up with.
And again, I said we have three pages.
So from the sales executive, like,
is this going to affect my follow-on business?
The original contracts were fair and reasonable,
so we felt like he did not.
His interest was that we didn't do anything wrong,
and we shouldn't be penalized.
You have a question?
Were we assuming that this was a big sale?
It was a big company,
but was it a big sale?
It was a big sale for little ink.
Not for big ink.
OK.
And again, for me, the relationship with the customer
was very important.
And I did want them to acknowledge
that we had done work.
I wanted them to say
that we were a competent company,
that they didn't cancel because of anything we did wrong.
So I was worried about our reputation.
OK.
And again, I did not want it to get escalated,
because I just thought that would make things more intense,
put it that way.
Our CFO was worried about cash flow.
She didn't want to get, again, lawyers.
Didn't want to look like she was inexperienced
and didn't know how to run a company.
But she did want it to be fair, and she
didn't want to be taken advantage of.
And she felt like we
did do a lot of work,
and those expenses should be covered.
So again, from big.
Yeah.
From a small business perspective,
we didn't want any of that.
We wanted to do a lot of work, and we
wanted to do a lot of work with our customers.
And we wanted to do a
lot of work with our customers.
So we did that.
But we didn't want to take any of that money.
And we didn't want to take any of that money.
So we just assumed that.
We assumed that because we had other contracts with them.
Again, we didn't know this, but this
is what we thought of in our meeting,
and which I tell people that they really
have to think a lot about.
And so we do那's what we did with our clients
to work together.
And we use that to contribute to the ви treasured
false change.
So the value is, someone else can't give
us any lead, and we can do that.
We can do it ourselves.
This is what I saw on our chat, where
started the meeting and Raz and I just
came into a conversation and ourхc
little speaker phones, the little triangle things,
and we call them, and you
can feel the tension in the air.
And he says, you know, we say hello,
and then they say, they come up and they say,
we want this much money back.
And our CFO looks up and he says, okay.
And that was the end.
So this is a class on negotiation.
What kind of negotiation was that?
What are your thoughts?
We just agreed to the very first thing they said.
Why?
Yes.
Because it was better than you would expect it.
So we had thought in advance
what our solution space could be.
We had thought and really she had calculated out
how much she could afford, what would it do.
And the thing is, is everything, you know,
typically when I teach this, I
get a lot of pushback saying,
hey, you should have at least pushed
back a little bit more.
And I say, you know,
I'm not going to push back
because you're not doing the fiduciary responsibility
for your company, but what were our interests?
What were our real interests?
I mean, obviously we're interested in the financial safety
of the company, but we wanted to keep the relationship.
And we didn't know if we push back,
if everything would fall down.
So I have another colleague who
tells us the exact same story
with his company and they were negotiating, negotiating,
and they did, they tried for one more thing.
And the whole thing blew up in his face.
The company took their toys and went to another vendor
and they never worked together again.
So you just never know.
And you don't want to, we didn't want to push
because it worked for us.
We thought it was fair.
We could see that in their offer,
they didn't want to stomp on us.
They weren't trying to be
punitive to us for any reason.
And what happened was we continued the relationship
for many years and they bought more later.
So thoughts on this?
And you know, when I have
a colleague who worked at 3M
and he said, looked at me, he said,
sometimes the first offer is the best offer.
And if it's something that you can live with
and we preserve the relationship and after that,
we're going to have a new business.
Now, there's a lot of corporations
that didn't really have this idea.
And still fundamental thinking components
for how you Ctrl to publicize the value
that it left for compensation like
whether it is an uniform application
or if it's a comparatively large grant amount,
this is a far betterYour own
idea.
So I'm like, okay, I'm like
. You send that on my email.
you're explicit about what you want and everyone knows
what they want and they talk about it it's
a lot easier to find an agreement
but it often feels that giving that information
could make the other part use it as a weapon
against you and i wonder like how do you gauge
like like in this uh scenario do you think
there was there would have been space to explicitly say
the things that are listed here to fake ink or
you just have to accept that you cannot be that
open with the person you're negotiating with okay okay
let me tell you one more story that answers
that question so i was advising another person so she
was a big ink trying to buy a little ink
because little ink had some ip that absolutely
everybody in her field was after right so it
took her six months to get a meeting with him
and so i said to her why don't you
plan out everything and think about what his interests are
what your interests are think about everything
you're gonna say and think about everything he
might say because now you know like everybody
is after him right because he's got something that
everybody wants so you know and he'd been
talking to other companies and so she she
calls me up afterwards she has this meeting with
her team and she she goes through this and she
go walks in the door and the first thing the guy
says to her you know they they come in this is
she's waited six months to have like you know an
hour meeting with him and he literally looks at her
doesn't say hello he goes what do you want
literally and she starts in by saying you know
we thought that you might be interested
in having your your intellectual property get more
better dec amateur access your knowledge we
know you have sign language lernen haven't you
done this before we're going to have our real
world work and it was crazy right so the part
of her group since we were young
which sank early with two of us now
was we had to go through the differentiation where
teacher steve always tells me this here
you have peerless teachers don't know it like
to work in your description do you
get a落ch荷 280 00001 don't you know people
students these days they really don't know
some of the stuff especially with the gestalt
is sp workers and so i'm thinking out of
the box if a case isınız there somehow that i'm
going to look into some that you can talk
to if you know anything about education in theaters
i'll call it which you could figure out pretty
simple at a small course bless you every morning
So basically she started out
with interests and discussing it.
And when he saw that she was
interested in his interests and helping him
and that it was a joint problem to solve,
they got the business and she got a promotion.
So it depends on how you start.
And then my 3M buddy, he's
had all these negotiations with IBM.
And he said one time it wasn't going at all.
And he said, let's, he talked, you
know, these are both have stables of lawyers.
And he said, well, let's
talk about what we're interested in.
No, no, we're just going to negotiate.
And things weren't moving.
Things weren't moving at all.
And so he finally just said, well, 3M
is interested in doing this kind of thing.
And he just started giving them their interests.
And we're interested in this.
And they changed.
They turned and they started sharing their interests.
So I think you're right.
You could use it as a weapon.
But if you're really trying,
as a joint problem that you can share your interest.
You don't have to say, I need this deal with
IBM because otherwise 3M is going to go out of business.
I mean, those things you don't share.
Right.
But you can share the things
that will help move it forward.
Does that help?
Okay.
Go ahead.
We have two more minutes, but go ahead.
Okay.
I know this is a condition.
So I'm going to ask you
to share your interest, your interest.
So let's say for this example, you have three interests of
individuals and then four of the big interests in the company.
And when it comes to business negotiations, when you get into this room, I would assume that if you
know who the people are going to be there, it's kind of like a little bit easier to potentially prepare.
But if you get into the room and you have people
that you did not expect to see, how do you tackle this?
Meaning that you just don't know.
Or the interest will be your trust.
Is this from the business interest or
still taking into account the risk concept?
Well, I guess you can.
Well, first of all, you're saying right.
Because the person we were talking
to had different interests than Big Inc.
Right.
I mean, we could have put, you know, the
people that were going to be in the room.
But if this had been like, let's talk about our interests, I would
have said, oh, you're probably interested in making sure that this is working.
So you can actually ask people.
And so when I'm even in a mediation,
I'll just ask them, well, what are your interests?
You know, what is important to you?
What are you trying to accomplish?
What would be helpful to you?
And if people don't want to share, then you can see which way the
negotiation may not go so far because you don't even know what to offer them.
Right.
Because there might be things that
I mean, this is the whole point.
There might be things that are so
valueless to you, but they're valuable to them.
And they say, well, we
want your company to do X.
And you're like, OK, like because
it's not a big deal for you.
Right.
So those are it's how do you get to those things that are sort of low
value to one person, high value to the other or things that you you can talk about.
So is this helpful?
OK.
Summary startups, make sure that you
understand the interests of your co-founder.
Right.
That's really important.
You know, document your decisions.
Because someday you're going to go,
well, why did we do that?
Right.
So I tell people, write everything down and revisit it periodically because companies change
really fast and your ideas change fast and you need to keep keep going.
And then for negotiations, just prepare, prepare, prepare.
What has been shown is the more that you think about what your
interests are, what their interests are, what your zone of solution it could be.
And listen in the in the meeting.
You know, you're going to have to make sure
that you're going to be able to do it.
And then in the meeting, you'll hear new interest.
You'll say, oh, you guys are interested in this.
I didn't know that.
Well, we might be interested in
helping you with that aspect, too.
So you're always listening and
thinking about what you can do.
All right.
I think that's it.
So thank you very much.
I hope this was helpful.
Mindy, great.
Thank you.
There's so many little tidbits of knowledge here.
And it brought back a memory I had.
I was there were three of us on one side.
Negotiating this divestiture of a whole division.
And we were the little little company was big, but little compared
to the big company that had like ten people at the table.
And we did a little
introduction, you know, like who's who.
How are you?
And it became pretty clear that these ten people had
flown in from all different parts of the country, our company.
And they probably hadn't really talked to each other.
So after the introductions, we suggested, you know.
You guys have just arrived.
Maybe a little want a little time to, you know, we
could give you some room to, you know, get organized and everything.
And we went out for about an hour.
And during that time, they actually
managed to talk and get organized enough.
So we had a really interesting discussion before.
Otherwise, it was pretty clear that, you know, somebody was going
to say something and somebody else is going to say something else.
And it wasn't going to go anywhere.
So you brought back that memory about interest.
Make sure the other
side understands their internal interests.
You know, people from different sides are trying to
And again, I try and ran over Mr.
Brad, theded Brother
and have a good evening.
Thank you.